Webinan (15 June 2017 [beta1])

   Identify potential outliers using a geostatistical framework.

   Webinan is a simple, pragmatic, heuristic algorithm. One-by-one we 
   visit each observation. We temporarily remove this observation from 
   the data set. We also temporarily remove all of the observations in 
   the immediate vicinity of this observation. With this reduced data 
   set we interpolate the value at this observation location using 
   Ordinary Kriging. 

   We compare the interpolated value with the observed value. If they 
   are significantly different, the observation is a potential outlier. 

Usage:
   Webinan <nugget> <sill> <range> <radius> <input file> <output file>
   Webinan --help
   Webinan --version

Arguments:
   <nugget>        The <nugget>, or 'nugget effect', is the discontinuity 
                   in the variogram at a lag of 0. The <nugget> quantifies 
                   the variance of the sampling and measurement errors and 
                   the hyper-local spatial variation. The units of the 
                   <nugget> are the units of the observed values squared. 
                   The <nugget> must be a strictly positive value. 

   <sill>          The <sill> is the value (height) at which variogram 
                   levels out. With the exponential model used in Webinan, 
                   the variogram approaches the <sill> asymptotically. 
                   In the common geostatistical framework (i.e. a second 
                   order stationary model), the sill equals the variance 
                   of the underlying population. The units of the <sill>
                   are the units of the observed values squared. The <sill>
                   must be a strictly positive value. 

   <range>         The <range> is the separation distance at which we 
                   model two observations as essentially uncorrelated. 
                   With the exponential model used in Webinan, this is 
                   the separation distance at which the variogram reaches 
                   95% of the <sill>. The units of the <range> are the 
                   units of the observations locations. The <range> must 
                   be a strictly positive value. 

   <radius>        The <radius> is the radius of the circle defining the 
                   'immediate vicinity' of each observation. When we 
                   interpolate the value at an observation location we 
                   exclude all of the observations that fall within a 
                   circle centered on the observation location with a 
                   radius equal to <radius>. The units of the <radius> are 
                   the units of the observations locations. The <radius> 
                   must be a non-negative value. 

   <input file>    The <input file> is the name of the file (including any 
                   necessary path information and the .csv file extension) 
                   containing the observation data. (See below.)

   <output file>   The <output file> is the name of the file (including 
                   any necessary path information and the file extension) 
                   where Webinan will write all of the program results. 
                   If the specified <output file> already exists, it will 
                   be overwritten. (See below.) 

Example:
   Webinan 3 25 3500 50 .\data\Input.csv Output.csv

Input:
   All of the observation data are supplied to Webinan by the <input file>.
   The <input file> must be a valid .csv format, using a single comma as 
   the field delimiter.

   The <input file> contains NO header lines. The <input file> may include 
   blank lines. The <input file> may include comment lines. Comment lines 
   are identified by an octothorpe (#) or an exclamation mark (!) in the 
   first column of the line.

   The <input file> contains one line for each observation. Each observation 
   line has four fields. 

   <ID>            The specified observation unique identification string.
                   The ID string can contain numbers, letters, underscores, 
                   and internal spaces. The ID may NOT contain commas.

   <X>             The specified observation location x-coordinate. The <X>
                   must be a valid floating point number.

   <Y>             The specified observation location y-coordinate. The <Y>
                   must be a valid floating point number.

   <Z>             The specified observation value a location (X,Y). The <Z>
                   must be a valid floating point number.

   The four fields must delimited by a single comma, or a single comma and 
   one or more spaces. Spaces and tabs are the start and end of fields are 
   trimmed. 

Output:
   All of the program results go to the <output file>. The <output file> 
   is written in a valid .csv format, using a single comma as the field 
   the field delimiter.

   The <output file> contains one standard header line. Following the header 
   lines there is one line for each observation in the <input file>. Each 
   observation line has nine fields. 

   <ID>            The specified observation identification string as 
                   given in the <input file>.

   <X>             The specified observation location x-coordinate as 
                   given in the <input file>.

   <Y>             The specified observation location y-coordinate as 
                   given in the <input file>.

   <Z>             The specified observation value at location (X,Y) as 
                   given in the <input file>.

   <Count>         The number of observations used in the interpolation.
                   The <Count> is the number of observations remaining 
                   after excluding the observations within the immediate 
                   vicinity of the observation location. 

   <Zhat>          The interpolated value at the observation location.

   <Kstd>          The 'standard error' of the interpolated value at the 
                   observation location. The <Kstd> is the square root 
                   Ordinary Kriging variance.

   <Zeta>          The <Zeta> is the normalized interpolation error. 
                      <Zeta> = (<Z> - <Zhat>)/<Kstd>.

   <pValue>        A small <pValue> indicates a potential outlier; e.g. 
                   a <pValue> less than 0.01. The <pValue> is defined as 
                   the probability that a standard normal random variable 
                   is more extreme than <Zeta>. 
                     if <Zeta> < 0 then 
                        <pValue> = Pr( standard normal < <Zeta> ) 
                     else if <Zeta> > 0 then 
                        <pValue> = Pr( standard normal > <Zeta> ) 

Notes:
   o  An exponential semivariogram model is used. 
         gamma(h) = <nugget> + (<sill>-<nugget>)*(1 - exp(-3h/<range>)) 

   o  The set of observations may include 'duplicates', i.e. multiple 
      observation values at the same location. 

   o  The project name 'Webinan' is the Ojibwe word for the inanimate 
      transitive verb 'throw it away'. See [http://ojibwe.lib.umn.edu]. 
      This name seems appropriate for a program used to identify potential 
      outliers.

Authors:
   R. Barnes, University of Minnesota          
   R. Soule,  Minnesota Department of Health   
